Guide to the Leopold Hotel records 1901-1984
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Leopold Hotel records
1901-1984
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0182LeopoldRecords
Leopold Hotel (Bellingham, Wash.)
9 linear ft.
The collection comprises the corporate, financial, and personnel records from the Leopold Hotel (formerly the Byron Hotel), dating from the early-1900s to the 1980s. There are materials related to early bond- and stockholders, as well as a wealth of information about two of the hotels' managers: John C. Pierce (1936-1960) and George Knowles (1960-1979).
The Leopold Hotel in Bellingham, Washington, was originally called the Byron Hotel but was renamed in honor of Leopold Schmidt, financial backer and heaviest stockholder in the Byron Hotel.
The Leopold Hotel records include corporate, financial, personnel records, architectural drawing and photographs dating between 1902-1984. There is early bondholder and stockholder information for the 1920s, as well as a wealth of information about two of the hotels managers: John C. Pierce (1936-1960) and George Knowles (1960-1979).
Unfortunately, the records are fragmented and in no way cover the long life of the hotel.
The Leopold Hotel records are organized according to the following series arrangment:
Series I. Corporate Records 1902-1980
Series II. Financial Records 1909-1984
Series III. Personnel Records 1950-1983
Series IV. Architectural Drawings undated
Series V. Photographs circa 1901-1978
Some restrictions apply - contact repository for details.
Materials donated by George Knowles, date unknown.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Byron Hotel (Bellingham, Wash.); Leopold Hotel (Bellingham, Wash.)
Bellingham (Wash.)--History--Sources
Business enterprises--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources; Hotels--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources
Bellingham; City and Town Life.
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Corporate Records, 1902-1980; Series I
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1902; 1952; 1979
    - Bylaws of the Byron Hotel, 1902 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Name change from Byron Hotel to Leopold Hotel, 1952 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Articles and Papers of Dissolution, 1979 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Board of Trustees, 1902-1929
    - Oath of Office, 1902 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - First Meeting, 1902 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Meeting Minutes (including By-laws), 1903; 1912; 1918; 1920 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Ledger – Important Papers of the Byron hotel (original copy), 1902-1929 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Ledger – Important Papers of the Byron Hotel (not original), 1902-1929 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Stock/Share Holders, 1904-1978
    - Meeting Minutes (includes information on name change), 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1952-1960 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Annual Stockholders Meeting Minutes, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Proxy Notices (regarding shareholders meetings), 1958-1959; 1962-1964; 1967-1968; 1970-1971; 1975; 1977 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Correspondence, 1904; 1912-1966 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Directors Meeting Minutes, 1949-1978
    - Minutes, 1949; 1951-1960 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Minutes, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Minutes, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Minutes, 1970; 1971; 1975-1978 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Manager's General Information, 1936-1980
    - General Correspondence, 1936-1980 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - Western Hotels International Managers Meetings, 1955; 1957; 1960-1961; 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Western Hotels International – Management Agreement Termination, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 1/23)
- Financial Records, 1909-1984; Series II
  - Financial Statements, 1939-1979
    - Statements, 1939-1959 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Statements, 1960-1973 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Statements, 1974 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Statements, 1975 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Statements, 1976 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Statements, 1977 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Statements, 1978 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Statements, 1979 (Box-folder 1/31)
    - General Journal, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
    - General Journal, 1973-1977; 1979 (Box 3)
  - General Ledger, 1928-1956; Folders 4/1 - 4/12 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - A File – Accounts Payable, Accounts Receivable, Accrued Interest Payable/Receivable, Accrued Payroll, Accrued Sub-rents, Accrued Taxes, Accrued Telephone, Administrative Expense, Advertising, Auto Club of Washington (Box-folder 4/1)
    - B File – Bad Checks/Debts, Baggage Bank (General Payroll), Bellingham Bay Improvement Co. (BBIC), Beer Expense/ Services/ Sales/Wages, Bellingham Hotel, Beverage Issues/ Sales, Building Alterations and Improvements/ Finances, Building Tulip Room (Box-folder 4/2)
    - C File – Café (Alterations and Improvements/ Advertising and Printing/ Employee Meals/ Equipment/ Purchases/ Food Cost/ Entertainment/ General Expenses/ Heat/ Laundry/ Light and Power/ Maintenance/ Receipts/ Wages/ Water), Capital/ Common Stock, Carr Insurance Co., Sabine L. Case, Cash Over and Short, Cigar Counter Purchases/ Receipts, Commissions, Contract Payable, Coal, Custom Cleaners. (Box-folder 4/3)
    - D File – Deferred Expenses, Discount and Commission on Bonds, Dividends Payable, Donations, Due Stock Subscriptions (Box-folder 4/4)
    - E, F, G, and H Files – Employee Meals/ Rooms, Estimated Income, Exchange, Ferndale Power Association Bond, First National Bank, Foundation Salary, Furniture and Texture/ Laundry Operations, General Unapportioned Expense, E.A. Grant Co., Grill Expense, Group Life Insurance, Guest Charges, Heat/ Light/ Power and Refrigeration (Box-folder 4/5)
    - I File – Imprest Funds, Insurance, Interest, Inventory (Box-folder 4/6)
    - J, K, and L Files – C.C. Jerstedt, J.M. Kenney, Kitchen Equipment, Lamps, Laundry, Legal Expenses, Light and Power, Linen Store Rooms, Liquor, Lowery and Miscellaneous Garage (Box-folder 4/7)
    - M and N Files – Maintenance, Malta Thurston Hotels Inc., Malted Milk Shop, Misc. Income, Mitchell Hotel, Mortgage, Mount Baker Development, Mt. Vernon Hotel Co., New Building, New Governor Hotel, New Washington Hotel, Notes Payable, Mable Armstrong, W.G. Melne (Box-folder 4/8)
    - O, P, and Q Files – Occupational Disease Tax, Officers Salaries, Old Age Employee Benefits, Olympian Hotel, Organization Expense, Pacific Coast Investment Co., Pacific Coast Paper Mills Stock, Pacific Telephone and Telegraphy Co., Payroll Distribution, Pay Collections, George Pierce Barber Shop, Pierce Bros. Inc., Porters, Preferred Stock Subscription, Prepaid Insurance, Prepaid License, Prepaid Mortgage Expense, Prepaid Sign Rent, Prepaid Taxes, Profit and Loss (Box-folder 4/9)
    - R File – Real Estate, Rent, Reserve for Taxes, Restaurant Expenses, Restaurant Receipts, Returned Checks, Rodmans, Room Earnings and Expenses (Box-folder 4/10)
    - S and T Files – Salaries, Sample Room Expense/ Earnings, San Juan Pulp and Paper Mill Stock, Sanitarium Baths, Peter G. Schmidt/ Schmidt Estate Inc., Henry Schupp, Seattle First National Bank, Stationary and Printing, N.J. Stevens and Co., Store and Other Rentals, Storeroom, Sublease Deposit/ Rents, Sundry Assets, Supervision, Surplus, Special Suspense, Taxes, Tacoma Hotel Stock, Telephone and Telegraph, S.W. Thruston, Paul F. Tiffany, Traveling Expense, Tulip Room Rentals (Box-folder 4/11)
    - U, V, X, W, Y, and Z Files – Unclaimed Dividend, Unemployment Insurance, U.S. Collector Internal Revenue, Victory Tax, War Bonds, Washington Hotel Co. Stock, Washington Mutual Savings, Washington State Sales Tax, Washington State Unemployment Insurance, Water, Western Hotels International, Western Union, With-holding Tax, Wood Fuel, Yellow Cat Company (Box-folder 4/12)
  - General Ledger, 1931-1962; Folders 4/13 - 4/19 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Liabilities, 1931-1962 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Accounts Payable, 1947-1961 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - Rooms, Food, Beverage, and Telephone Departments, 1961 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Administrative and General, Advertisement and Business Promotion, Payroll Taxes and Employee Relations, Heating Lighting and Power, Repairs and Maintenance, Rent, Taxes and Insurance, Misc. Income, Store Rentals, Federal Income Tax, Depreciations Interest, Payroll Distribution, 1961 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Current Assets, Fixed Assets, Prepayments, and Other Assets, 1962 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Liabilities, Capital, and Income, 1962 (Box-folder 4/18)
    - Operating Costs and Expenses, 1962 (Box-folder 4/19)
  - General Ledger, 1953-1955; Folder 4/20 was originally a bound volume.
    - Profit and Loss, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 4/20)
  - General Ledger, 1954-1959; Folders 4/21 - 4/24 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Profit and Loss (Box-folder 4/21)
    - Rooms Department, Food Department, Beverage Department, Telephone Department, Administrative and General, Advertising and Promotion (Box-folder 4/22)
    - Payroll Taxes and Employee Relations, Heating Lights and Power, Repairs and Maintenance, Rent Municipal Taxes and Insurance, Store Rentals (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Depreciation and Payroll Distribution (Box-folder 4/24)
  - General Ledger, 1960; Folder 4/25 was originally a bound volume.
    - Profit and Loss (Box-folder 4/25)
  - General Ledger, 1964-1965; Folders 5/1 - 5/5 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Liabilities (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Operating (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Food and Beverage Combined and Overhead (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Payroll Taxes, Employee Relations, and Total Labor Cost (Box-folder 5/5)
  - General Ledger, 1966; Folders 5/6 - 5/10 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets – Cash, Accounts Receivable, Inventories, Prepaid Expenses, Other Current Assets, Investments, Deposits, Furniture Fixtures and Equipment, Reserve for Duplication and Amortization, Land, Other Assets (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Liabilities – Accounts Payable, Accrued Expenditures, Accounts Payable, Western International Hotels, Federal Taxes on Income, Other, Notes Contracts and Mortgages Non-Affiliates, Net Worth, Profit and Loss (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Operating – Rooms, Food Department, Beverage Department, Telephone, Cigar Stand, Other (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Overhead – Administrative and General, Advertising and Promotion, Heat Light and Power, Repair and Maintenance, Payroll Taxes and Employee Relations (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Payroll Taxes and Total Labor Costs – Sub-Rental Income, Local Taxes and Insurance, Interest Expense, Depreciation Amortization, Federal and State Income Tax Expenses (Box-folder 5/10)
  - General Ledger, 1967-1978; Folders 5/11 - 5/16 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets - Cash, Accounts Receivable, Inventories, Paid Expenses, Other, Investments, Deposits (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Work in Progress and Liabilities (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Operating – Rooms, Food and Beverage Depts (Box-folder 5/13)
    - Food and Beverage Combined (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Overhead (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Payroll Taxes, Employee Relations Exhibit, and Total Labor Costs Exhibit (Box-folder 5/16)
  - General Ledger, 1969; Folders 5/17 - 5/19 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 5/17)
    - Operating (Box-folder 5/18)
    - Food and Beverage Combined, Overhead, Payroll Taxes, Employee Relations Exhibit, and Total Labor Costs Exhibit (Box-folder 5/19)
  - General Ledger, 1970; Folders 6/1 - 6/3 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Operating – Rooms, Food, Beverage, Telephone, and Other (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Overhead, Payroll Taxes/Employee Relations Exhibit (Box-folder 6/3)
  - General Ledger, 1971; Folders 6/4 - 6/6 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Operating - Rooms, Food, Beverage, Telephone, and Other (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Overhead, Payroll Taxes/ Employee Relations Exhibit (Box-folder 6/6)
  - General Ledger, 1972; Folders 6/7 - 6/9 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 6/8)
    - Overhead and Payroll Taxes/ Employee Relations Exhibit (Box-folder 6/9)
  - General Ledger, 1973-1975; Folders 6/10 - 6/14 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 6/10)
    - Operating – Food (Box-folder 6/11)
    - Operating – Beverage, Food, and Other (Box-folder 6/12)
    - Overhead (Box-folder 6/13)
    - Payroll Taxes and Employee Relations Charged to Departments (Box-folder 6/14)
  - General Ledger, 1976-1978; Folders 6/15 - 6/16 are parts of a general ledger that was originally a bound volume.
    - Assets and Liabilities (Box-folder 6/15)
    - Operations and Overhead (Box-folder 6/16)
    - General Ledger, 1977 (Box-folder 6/17)
    - General Ledger, 1978 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - Stock, 1928-1979
    - Stockholder’s Ledger, 1928-1979 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Preferred Stock Certificates #1-99, 1928-1940 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Preferred Stock Certificates #101-168 (missing 152 and 157), 1941-1971 (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Common Stock Certificates #1-100, 1912-1964 (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Common Stock Certificates #101-139, 1964-1979 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Correspondence Governor, Capital and Olympian Hotels (includes financial statements and reports), 1949-1951 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Option Agreements between Byron/Leopold Hotel and Pacific Coast Investment Company or Maltby Thurston Company or Western Hotels International (details purchase of Capital and Olympian Hotel Stock by John C. Pierce), 1947-1953 (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Voting Trust Certificates, 1949 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Agreements, 1910-1984
    - Property Agreements and Warranty Deeds, 1910; 1912; 1915; 1925; 1928; 1947; 1958-1960 (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Mortgages, 1915; 1920; 1930; 1947; 1954; 1955; 1960 (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Insurance Contracts, 1949 (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Corporate Licenses, 1952; 1953; 1955; 1956; 1975-1979 (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Management Agreement with Western Hotels International (includes mortgage information), 1960 (Box-folder 7/13)
    - Legal (Pacific Northwest Bell litigation about termination charges), 1982-1984 (Box-folder 7/14)
    - Loans with Seattle First National Bank, 1954-1978 (Box-folder 7/15)
  - Appraisals, 1935; 1972; 1977
    - Appraisals (includes photos and blue prints), 1935 (Box-folder 7/16)
    - Appraisals, 1972 (Box-folder 7/17)
    - Appraisals, 1977 (Box-folder 7/18)
  - Taxes, 1909-1979
    - Personal Property and Real Estate, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 7/19)
    - Personal Property and Real Estate, 1971-1979 (Box-folder 7/20)
    - Excise, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 7/21)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 7/22)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 7/23)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 7/24)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1977 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1978 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Income Tax Returns, 1979 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - FICA Quarterly Reports, 1974 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - FICA Quarterly Reports, 1978 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - FICA Quarterly Reports, 1979 (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Miscellaneous Finance and Expense File, 1909-1928 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Accounts Payable on Loans, 1947-1957 (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Miscellaneous Financial Papers, 1955-1978 (Box-folder 8/11)
- Personnel Records, 1950-1983; Series III
  Some restrictions apply - contact repository for details.
  - Employee Information Index Cards, 1950s-1970s (Box 9)
  - Labor Distribution, Undated (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Corporate Pension Plan, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Culinary Workers & Bartenders Local No. 451 Contract, 1974-1976; 1976-1979 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Culinary Workers & Bartenders Local No. 451 Benefit Programs, 1969; 1972; 1977; 1978 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Payroll Journal, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Payroll Journal, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Payroll Journal, 1977 (Box 13)
  - Payroll Journal, 1978 (Box 14)
  - Payroll Journal, January, 1979-June 1979 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - Payroll Account 35102-011(closed), 1979 (Box-folder 15/2)
- Architectural Drawings, Undated; Series IV
  - Rolled Copy of Leopold Hotel Blue Prints, Undated (Box 15)
- Photographs, 1901-1978; Series V
  - Photographs of the Leopold Hotel and its Employees, circa 1913-1977 (Volume Volume 1)
  - Photographs of the Leopold Hotel and its Employees, circa 1901-1978 (Box Volume 2)